A Guide to the Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1923-1930
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1923-1930
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6220-e
This collection consists of 26 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in 1973.
Contents List
- Theodore Dreiser, Monticello, New York, to Sallie Kussell, New York 1923 Aug 4, ALS. 4 p. w/env.
  Calls her "My Little Yankee Zulu"; mentions classic tragedy they discussed, and a letter from Liveright; thinks of her often; plans to work with her.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, to Sallie Kussell 1923 Aug 4, APCS, 1 p.
  Depicts Tri-State Monument in Port Jervis, New York with a line about man sitting on bench.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Monticello, New York, to Sallie Kussell, New York 1923 Aug 7, ALS, 4 p. W/env.
  Asks if she knew that Mrs. Dreiser's first name was Sallie; wishes for her patience; needs her encouragement and criticism as he works on [ An American Tragedy]; mentions [H. L.] Mencken, illness, and cabin in the woods; plans to send 6 chapters and would like her opinion of them.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Monticello, New York, to Sallie Kussell, New York 1923 Aug 9, ALS, 2 p. W/env
  Hopes Liveright will come across with something; fells depressed; wished for her company; compliments her maternal understanding and sympathy.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Monticello, to Sallie Kussell, New York [1923] Aug 10, ALS, 3 p. W/env.
  Wishes he could see her; compliments her talk; describes natural surroundings.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Monticello, to Sallie Kussell, New York 1923 Aug 16, ALS, 8 p. W/env.
  Discusses his struggles with [ An American Tragedy]; mentions Shakespeare and Ann Hathaway.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Monticello, to Sallie Kussell, New York [1923 Aug 18], ALS, 1 p. W/env.
  Encloses proof of article The Nordic Blond Renaissance, by H. L. Mencken; mentions delays; plans to return and see her Sunday or Monday.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to w/envSallie Kussell, Chicago 1923 Aug 24, ALS, 4 p.
  Asks about Chicago; asks if he is forgiven; calls her soul dark and passionate; hopes show and trip go well; mentions circular H. L. Mencken sent him about impotency.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Chicago 1923 Aug 25, ALS, 4 p.
  Discusses their relationship; believes he could make her happy, but not indefinitely; wishes he could solve all her problems.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Chicago [1923 Aug 25], ALS, 1 p. W/env.
  Believes 64 page chapter was too late, as he wanted to go over it with her; wishes he had seen her today.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Chicago 1923 Aug 27, ALS, 4 p. W/env.
  Apologizes for not being in stateroom with her; compliments her gift for suggesting the sensual, her ideas, and her idealism; wishes he could write a chapter a day of [ An American Tragedy]; asks her to practice telepathy on him to speed his work.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to carbonArthur Vance, Carl Van Doren, Henry S. Canby, Alfred Knopf, William H. Briggs, and Burton Rascoe, New York [ca. 1924 Jan 16], TLS, 1 p.
  Writes letter of recommendation for Sallie Kussell, who assisted him in a literary and editorial capacity of almost a year; mentions her work in play construction; lists her qualifications and suggests they may have a place for her.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Sallie Kussell], New York 1924 Jan 16, ALS, 2 p. Draft w/env.
  Sends copy of recommendation letter to her; includes list of people to send it to; includes corrections.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont, New York 1925 Dec 7, ALS, 2 p. W/env.
  Includes cleaning receipt for fur coat; expresses gratitude toward tailor who repaired it; plans to leave for mountains; calls Saturday a grand occasion.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Petersburg, Virginia, to Sallie Kussell, New York 1925 Dec 14, APCS, 1 p.
  Asks her to drop note to General Delivery Winston-Salem, North Carolina.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Waycross, w/envGeorgia, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont, New York 1925 Dec 23, ALS, 4 p.
  Describes travels in Georgia; mentions mail and book; asks her to look for an apartment for him between 59th and 72nd Street; makes romantic suggestions, signed "Pedestrian" or "The outcast author."
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, St. Augustine, Florida, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont, New York 1925 Dec 30, Telegram, 1 p.
  Asks her to write him at General Delivery Fort Lauderdale, Florida.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Ft. Lauderdale, Florida, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont, New York 1926 Jan 5, ALS, 9 p. W/env.
  Expresses pleasure at being in Florida after Georgia; mentions cold spell, vegetation, criticism of [ An American Tragedy], his inability to write letters, proximity of the Everglades, population of 5,000, and $200,000,00 construction project; thinks of her; writes that he received telegram from Liveright to say book is starting off pretty well.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Ft. Lauderdale, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont 1926 Jan 8, APCS, 1 p.
  Depicts Coral Gables; signed "The Prince of Whales."
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont 1926 Feb 13, ALS, 3 p. W/env.
  Believes that trouble between them stems from conviction that her interest in him is based on desire for recognition through him; discusses book inscription; mentions his silence.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont 1926 Dec 22, ALS, 1 p. W/env.
  Writes that if she spends the New York check, he will have to see what he can do about it.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New Jersey, to Sallie Kussell, New York [1927 Mar 25], ALS, 3 p. W/env.
  Describes his walk from Farmwood to Bound Brook;asks her to write to Gettysburg, Pennsylvania; asks her to send revised cover of Chains.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Easton, Pennsylvania, to Sallie Kussell 1927 Mar 27, ALS, 2 p.
  Mentions snow and rain in Easton; asks her to draft a letter for him to sign; describes trip in detail; gives route to Blue Ridge in West Virginia; asks her to get information on Dryden and to look after Chains and The Financier.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Lancaster, w/envPennsylvania, to Sallie Kussell, New York [1927] Apr 2, ALS, 3 p.
  Encloses note from Reading, Pennsylvania, March 30; asserts that nothing is wrong other than strain of traveling; mentions weight loss, arch-support shoe and disagreeable weather; likes covers, but wants script used for text on covers without boxes; discusses physical and mental information from [H. L.] Mencken; describes photos of Mennonite Dutch men his age who live between Allentown and Lancaster.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, Martinsburg, Virginia, to Sallie Kussell, New York 1927 Apr 9, ALS, 1 p. W/env.
  Plans to leave for Winchester, Virginia; mentions snow, turned ankle, Anderson; plans to walk 23-25 miles daily, while he has solitude on trip; expects to return in 10 days.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Sallie Kussell, Larchmont 1930 Sep 3, ALS, 1 p. W/env.
  Expresses pleasure upon receiving greeting as he would not have recalled it was 7 years.
- Letter from Theodore Dreiser to Sallie Kussell Jun 17, ALS, 2 p.
  Asks if it is lost, strayed, stolen, or a lesson to him as the Negro on the gallows observed; asks her to write or call the Guardian Life Building in care of Arthur Hume; writes that he has been laid up for 2 days due to bad burn.